Guide to the Olga Rudge Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
There are almost no letters between July 1955 and the spring of 1959. Pound's letters resume with discussion of moving his belongings from Sant'Ambrogio to Brunnenburg. The letters from 1959 to 1962 are located in folders 863 to 873 and trace Pound's declining health and mood. A late 1959 letter notes that "INSIDE was where he belonged for COMFORT, and no responsibility able to think soap bubble and be lord of creation with no fuss." Some letters express regret for past actions and affection for Rudge. Rudge's notes are brief inquiries and attempts to cheer him.
Boxes 31 and 32 contain empty envelopes found with the Pound-Rudge correspondence. They have been arranged in roughly chronological order by decade.
Series II, General Correspondence, fills Boxes 33-92 and consists of the alphabetically arranged correspondence of Olga Rudge. Individuals represented by four or more items have received separate listings; the letter general files usually contain routine letters such as requests for autographs, Christmas cards, isolated business letters, and single notes. Unidentified correspondence has been placed toward the end of the series, in Boxes 83 and 84, followed by empty envelopes addressed to Rudge and a small section of alphabetically arranged third-party correspondence.
Pound lived with Rudge from 1962 to 1972, and correspondents often addressed letters to "Ezra Pound and Olga Rudge," "Ezra and Olga Pound," and other combinations. All of these letters are retained in the Olga Rudge Papers. Letters specifically addressed to Ezra Pound alone have been processed with the Ezra Pound Addition (YCAL MSS 53).
Family correspondents in the Olga Rudge Papers include Rudge's parents, brother, daughter, grandchildren, and various cousins. The correspondence with Julia O'Connell Rudge consists of letters exchanged while Rudge was a student at St. Anthony's Convent in Sherborne. Her letters describe school events, studies, and her relations with the other girls. Julia Rudge's letters offer sympathy, advice, and details of her own life and emotional state. The only surviving letters from J. Edgar Rudge discuss money he sent to his daughter and the financial difficulties he faced during the Depression. A 1930 letter, written shortly after Rudge had purchased her Venice house with her father's assistance, notes "you will have to try and do something to earn a living. It is too bad if you cannot make it go with your music..."
Letters from Rudge's brother Teddy are located in Box 71, folders 1937-52. There are a few letters from the 1920s, but most of the correspondence is post-1950. The letters contain family news, travel plans, discussions of Teddy's medical practice and dislike of postwar socialized medicine, and the varying fortunes of a parking lot in Youngstown that the two had inherited. The postwar letters offer limited assistance to Rudge while advising her to distance herself from Pound: "The less you are involved the better," according to a late 1945 letter. Folders 1934-36 contain letters written by Teddy Rudge's son Peter. These usually contain news of his family and plans to visit Italy, but a 1948 letter from Brunnenburg describes the last illness of Isobel Pound.
Boxes 63-69 contain the correspondence of Rudge's daughter, Mary de Rachewiltz. Spanning the years 1930-1989, these letters document many aspects of Rudge's personal life and relationship with Pound. The earliest notes, written from Gais in the German dialect of the area and in school Italian, seem to contain mostly thanks for visits or presents and requests for letters; edelweiss is frequently enclosed. Beginning in 1937, Mary often writes from the Istituto delle Signore Montalve alla Quiete in Florence, the convent school that she attended until the Second World War. In Italian, English, and occasionally French, the letters discuss her studies, teachers, school friends, her foster family in Gais, and her hopes for visits with Rudge and Pound. A letter from November 1938, for example, contains the news that Mary has become a Daughter of Mary, reports on her language lessons, notes that "Babbo has sent me a book of poems of Robert Browning, very beautiful," and expresses her wish to spend her holidays with the Marchers in Gais.
As the war in Europe worsened, Mary's letters began to reflect its effects on her own life. Rudge refused to allow her to go to Gais in the fall of 1939, despite her desire to go and "help them, who, you know well, don't know how to speak Italian." Other letters note sewing for soldiers, prayers for peace, and films of "the German soldiers in Paris." Also in 1940, at Pound's urging, Mary began a series of translation exercises, some of which are included in these letters.
Mary left the Quiete in the summer of 1941 and joined her mother first in Siena and then in Sant'Ambrogio. She spent several months in Gais in the summer and fall of 1942, and her letters discuss food, the Marcher family, the effects of the war in Gais, and news from Pound. A series of Rudge's replies for these months, written in German, survives as well. Mary returned to Gais in the summer of 1943, and remained separated from her parents until the end of the war. Her letters from this period document the various jobs she held, the last in an army hospital in the Dolomites, food, Todt work, friends, reactions to the war news, and fears for her family. A July 1943 letter begins "Temo anche per E. [Pound] che probabilimente torneré a Roma," while a February 1944 letter comments "sono cosi contente che E. possa continuare la sua attività." Pound appears to have been in fairly regular contact with his daughter, and in early 1945 she received copies of his new Cantos, which she called "stupefacenti."
Letters from 1945-47 deal with Mary's reaction to Pound's arrest and detention, news received from Pound's friends in America, money worries, and Mary's plans for the future. A series of 1946 letters describes her relationship with Boris de Rachewiltz and ask for Rudge's approval, noting that "for a woman marriage is a necessary arrangement (in my opinion.)"
Later letters detail the early years of her marriage, the couple's move to Brunnenberg castle, the arrival of Isobel Pound there, and the birth of Mary's children. Other letters contain support for Rudge in her own difficulties, plans for Pound's release, and descriptions of the Pound students and admirers who visited Brunnenberg at his suggestion. There are several letters reporting on her 1953 visit to Pound in Washington, as well as letters of advice concerning Rudge's own visits.
The letters from 1958 to 1962 are especially informative concerning Pound's life after his return to Italy. They describe his daily activities, conversation, moods, and illnesses in some detail, and record Mary's reactions to his often difficult behavior. In addition to having Pound, his wife, and Marcella Spann at Brunnenberg, Mary received visits from researchers and scholars, and she sent news of these to Rudge, remarking in August 1959 "Have reread the Aspern Papers last night, God I have a mind to make a big bonfire and burn up every single scrap of paper."
After Pound joined Rudge in 1962, Mary's letters were devoted to family news, inquiries after their health, and discussion of the complex legal issues surrounding the Pound archive. The last letters in this group describe Mary's own work, travel, and her family's affairs,
The collection also contains letters to Rudge from Mary's children, Walter de Rachewiltz and Patrizia de Rachewiltz de Vroom. These contain school and family news, travel descriptions, arrangements for visits to Venice, and occasionally drawings and sketches.
Rudge's early life is not well represented in this series. There are letters from Ethel and Mabel Duncan, family friends of the Rudges, discussing social events in Paris and London, mutual acquaintances, and music. Mabel Duncan was one of the first people in Rudge's circle to learn of the birth of Mary Rudge, and her 1936 letters contain good wishes, gossip from Paris, and advice on the education and social life for Mary. Ethel Duncan's letters include descriptions of receptions for Charles Maurras, a 1935 warning that "Mussolini is not always right," and 1952 reports on her visit to Pound at St. Elizabeths. Another friend, Etta Glover, sent Rudge her thoughts on her relationship with Pound, advice, and descriptions of her life in Uganda. Other long-term friends represented in the correspondence include the Reverend Desmond Chute, Blanche Somers-Cocks, and Adrian Stokes.
Box 41, folders 1321-25 hold letters by Rudge's early suitor, the biologist Egerton Charles Grey. The first letter, dated 1916, consists of a long poem addressed to "Dear Olga." Other letters contain discussion of Grey's feelings for Rudge, reminiscences about their meetings in London and Paris, proposals of marriage, and responses to her rejections of them. The letters from 1928, the year of Grey's death, are brief friendly notes.
Rudge's musical career is documented in her correspondence with fellow musicians, including George Antheil, Renata Borgatti, Alfredo Casella, Kathleen Dale, Ralph Lawton, Ildebrando Pizzetti, and Tibor Serly; with her patrons Nadia Boulanger, Arturo Brown, and Katherine Dalliba-John; and with conte Guido Chigi-Saracini, Luciano Alberti, and Armando Vannini. Antheil's letters include invitations and arrangements for visits, proposals for concert tours with Rudge, and discussion of his own career plans. Borgatti wrote frequently about the difficulties of establishing her own career and sent on news of acquaintances in the Paris music circle. The letters of Casella and Pizzetti contain information about concert tours and arrangements to meet with Rudge.
While Rudge's relationship with Katherine Dalliba-John, founder of the Studio Meeting Society, began during World War I, most of the letters in the Rudge Papers date from Dalliba-John's last years in Florence. They concern visits, her declining health, and the financial troubles brought on by the Depression. A 1932 letter notes, "I am terribly worried about money, for America is going to the dogs!" Her 1935 May 26 letter expresses her appreciation for a profile of her by Pound that appeared in Il Mare. Arturo Brown's correspondence discusses concerts he financed for Rudge, the music scene in Paris, mutual friends, and his travels between France and his native Argentina.
Rudge's professional activities as secretary of the Accademia Chigiana can be traced in the letters of conte Guido Chigi-Saracini. Topics include the planning of concert schedules, the quality and temperaments of visiting musicians, the Accademia's financial situation, and the relations between Chigi and the governments of Siena. Letters from the late 1930s contain information on the microfilming of Vivaldi manuscripts and the Vivaldi studies and performances sponsored by the Chigiana, as well as references to Rudge's publicity work and the Concerti Tigulliani. Further information on the Vivaldi studies and publications can be found in the letters of S. A. Luciani.
Rudge knew and corresponded with many of Pound's colleagues and friends, particularly after his arrest and confinement in St. Elizabeths, including Olivia Agresti Rossetti, Stella Bowen, Julian Cornell, Ronald Duncan, Viola Jordan, John Kasper, Douglas Paige, Peter Russell, and Henry Swabey. Their letters contain expressions of sympathy for Pound's situation, reports on attempts to have him released, and descriptions of visits to him or letters from him. Rossetti, for instance, suggested in 1948 that Pound's "strong anti-Communist and anti-Russian stance" should be explained to the American ambassador to Italy. Cornell's letters explain his hopes of obtaining an early release for Pound and outline the legal and psychiatric difficulties.
There are more than thirty folders of letters from Pound's friend and publisher James Laughlin. Letters from the 1940s and 1950s describe Pound's condition, the legal and political obstacles to his release, efforts by the literary community to plead for his freedom, and "the atmosphere of the entourage" of visitors to St. Elizabeths. Laughlin wrote many letters attempting to explain the nuances of the treason charge and Pound's own attitude towards it. After Pound's return to Italy, Laughlin sent frequent medical and financial advice, reactions to various Pound interviews and scholarly projects, and news on Pound's American reputation. As Pound's publisher, he requested corrections to Cantos and text for Cantos 72 and 73, and offered his opinions on the merits of various "Pound projects."
T. S. Eliot's letters to Rudge contain substantial analysis of Pound's character, as well as descriptions of Eliot's visits to him. In 1948 he referred to Pound's current behavior as "an exaggeration of that impersonality and reticence which has always baffled me with him." Eliot also attempted to discourage what he considered ill-advised plans to publish the radio broadcasts, declined to supply letters for D. D. Paige's edition, and counseled Rudge about various strategies for Pound's release. He favored one plan which called for Pound's retirement to a monastery, for example, noting that "it will confuse the issues."
John Drummond's letters contain much information about the early efforts to find a lawyer for Pound, descriptions of efforts to free him, summaries of American attitudes toward him, and general commentary on Pound's character and opinions. After Pound's return to Italy, Drummond reported on his visits with him in 1960, noting that Pound was "beginning to think that in the past he may have been quite wrong about a lot of things."
Other major correspondents include Geoffrey Bridson, Guido Cadorin, Ferdinando Carpanini, William Cookson, Cyril Connolly, Desmond O'Grady, Lester Littlefield, Dorothy Pound, Sister Bernetta Quinn, Dachine Rainer, G. Singh, Vanni Scheiwiller, and Blanche Somers-Cocks. Much of the post-1962 correspondence concerns publication projects, tributes to Pound, and scholarly work.
Series III. Notebooks, has been divided into two sections: I Ching and Research Notebooks. Pound had a longstanding interest in the I Ching as a Confucian device, and after Pound joined Rudge in 1962 she began throwing the I Ching for each of them. As she described it in an entry for March 1966, "These hexagrams have always been made usually in morning first thing after breakfast. Commencing with mine. read aloud to E. Then his idem." The earliest surviving I Ching notes begin in 1966 and contain only the hexagrams thrown, but soon Rudge was using the notebooks to record significant details of their daily lives and activities. The notebooks from 1966 to Pound's death in 1972 are located in Box 93, folders 2480-491. Many of the notes concern Pound's health, diet, response to visitors, and remarks to Rudge. They also contain Pound's descriptions of his dreams and comments on these.
For example, the entry for 27 Nov. 1969 includes "Desmond and friends--Rev. Victor Stanley said grace. Paid E. a compliment on his poems--E said, 'You didn't find that in the 39 Articles.' Rev. V. asked if he thought Eliot was well acquainted with them--E. said he thought not." Eliot was still on Pound's mind on Dec. 28, when he dreamt that "he and Possum" were traveling and that "the luggage didn't match exactly." The entry for 8 Feb. 1972 describes Pound's reading of "What are years" at a memorial service for Marianne Moore and records a dream of Pound's that "Marianne was getting him a job.. .at Bryn Mawr."
After Pound's death, Rudge continued to throw the I Ching for both herself and Pound and to record the results. These journals can be found in Boxes 94-99. The daily entries were gradually expanded to include quotations from works by Pound, particularly from the Cantos and Guide to Kulchur; descriptions of Olga's daily activities; and reminiscences, commentary on books about Pound, and drafts of responses to letters. The notebooks record Rudge's responses to the visits of Pound scholars, her thoughts on family and friends, and her attempts to collect notes about Pound's life and works and to suggest likely publication projects for Pound's unpublished letters.For example, the notebook in Box 95, folder 2512, contains Rudge's memories of Pound's arrest and detention in Genoa, while the entry for 13 Sep 1976 (Box 95, folder 2518) describes her attempts to sort Pound's papers, quotes an Italian description of Mussolini's visit to Rapallo in December 1925, and adds her memory that "O. R. ...was curious & went down to rubber-neck arrival of Muss.-...E. P....was not interested enough to leave his desk and go down to see procession." While topics tend to recur, there is no apparent order to these journal entries.
Rudge's desire to "set the record straight" about some aspects of her life with Pound was the motive force behind the "Research Notebooks" located in Boxes 99-101. Many of these contain transcriptions of original material preserved in the Olga Rudge Papers, or lists of persons and subjects found in them. Box 101, folder 2603, holds "Transcriptions EP," Rudge's annotated copies of notebooks now located in the Ezra Pound Addition (YCAL 53). Notebooks of independent interest include "American Background" (Box 99, folder 2581), which contains Rudge's attempts to find parallels between her early life and Pound's, as well as other notes; Box 100, folder 2590, which contains letter drafts, comments on Rudge's early romance with the biologist Egerton Grey, a paragraph on the birth of Mary, and Richard Aldington's "romance a clé 'Nobody's Baby,'" and notes on various articles and books about Pound.
Series IV, Personal Papers, is housed in Boxes 102-24 and contains the personal papers of Olga Rudge, including address books and slips, calling cards, invitations to and announcements of various events, lists, notes, and writings.
Rudge in her later years attempted to document her life extensively. Some notes on her life can be found in Box 105, folders 2656-62, including a version of the events surrounding the birth of Mary Rudge. There is also an extensive section of "Notes on Pound," including six folders of biographical information, research and plans for various exhibits and tributes to Pound, and comments by Rudge on his writings. Folders 2783-84 contain information related to his medical condition after 1962; material concerning his funeral is located in folder 2782. While most of these notes were written by Rudge after Pound's death in 1972, folder 2786 contains brief listings of Pound's radio broadcasts heard by Rudge in 1942 and other information on those broadcasts later gathered by Rudge in Pound's defense.
Also of biographical interest are the agendas kept by Rudge from 1926 to 1987. These contain, typically, brief notes concerning appointments and errands. There are no agendas for the years 1931-47, and only 5 from the 1950s; after 1962 the sequence is intact, and these later items sometimes contain notes on Pound's health, mood, and activities.
There are only three actual diaries in the Rudge Papers (Box 106, folders 2675-77). The most complete is the earliest, which covers September and October 1931, when Rudge was living at Sant'Ambrogio. Entries detail her daily activities and conversations with Pound, her thoughts on their relationship, and notes on visitors to Rapallo. For example, the entry for October 28th contains Pound's comments on the utility of working in "a fit of rage," Rudge's comments on housekeeping in Rapallo, a discussion between Pound and Rudge on the birth of their daughter, and Rudge's thoughts on Pound's sensitivities and "line of conduct." The 1934 and 1943 diaries are much less complete, the 1934 one containing only a few pages on various events between June and August, while the 1943 notebook is largely devoted to the difficulty of obtaining food during war time and lists of meals.
Rudge was an energetic notetaker, particularly in the years after Pound's death, and this trait is illustrated by several folders of inventories of her possessions, "to-do" lists, and nine folders of scraps containing comments on her reading (Box 109, folders 2749-57). She also kept incomplete or rejected drafts of her own letters, and these are located in Box 107, folders 2704-18. Most of these date from the period after Pound's death. No attempt has been made to organize these fragments; complete drafts of letters to known recipients have been filed in Series II, General Correspondence, under the names of the recipients.
Memorabilia kept by Rudge is located in Box 108 and includes pressed flowers and leaves, matchbooks, hair, teeth, and a violin string.
Rudge's writings are located in Boxes 115-16 and include manuscripts, typescripts, and printed copies of articles by Olga Rudge. There are versions of several of her articles on Vivaldi, including "Lettere di Antonio Vivaldi" and her Vivaldi article for Grove's Dictionary of Music, and examples of her translation work, such as "England's War in France," which was corrected by Pound (folder 2831), and a typescript carbon of "Cantos d'Ezra Pound," an article by Louis Zukofsky. At Pound's urging, Rudge also attempted to translate the "Il Volto Santo" portion of Enrico Pea's Moscardino, and the incomplete manuscripts and typescripts of her version can be found in Box 115, folders 2834-43.
Both Rudge and Pound enjoyed reading mystery novels, and in the early 1930s they collaborated in writing one themselves, featuring an Inspector Love investigating a murder in Surrey. The incomplete drafts and versions of "The Blue Spill" are located in Box 115, folders 2814-24, and contain numerous manuscript corrections by the co-authors.
"Writings of Others" are housed in Boxes 117-19 and include poems, articles, books, and plays sent to Rudge over the years. Not surprisingly, many of these concern Ezra Pound, for example the galleys of Cyril Connolly's "Pound in Venice" (Box 117, folder 2868); Ilse Engel's "Story of a Meeting with Ezra Pound" (Box 117, folder 2872), and the draft typescript of Desmond O'Grady's "A Packet for W. B. Yeats from Ezra Pound" (Box 2896). Box 117, folder 2864 contains a typescript photocopy of Kenneth Arnold's play "The House of Bedlam," based on his imaginings of life at Sant'Ambrogio during World War II, which Rudge attempted to have suppressed. An autographed photocopy of Allen Ginsberg's reminiscences of his meeting with Pound and Rudge is located in Box 118, folder 2880.
Pound's friends and students are also well represented in this section. William Carlos Williams sent Rudge a signed, corrected typescript of his "Sketch for a Criticism: The XXX Cantos of Ezra Pound" in 1931 (Box 118. folder 2925). D. G. Bridson, Peter Russell, David Horton, and Henry Swabey also sent works of theirs, as did Pound scholars Donald Gallup, Hugh Kenner, and Patricia Hutchins.
Rudge received many poems as well, some of then concerning or dedicated to her, from authors including Dachine Rainer, G. Singh, and Piero Boschetti. Other items of interest include Robert Fitzgerald's "Memorandum for Mary," a 1954 piece in which he comments at length on the charges of treason against Pound and his confinement in St. Elizabeth's (Box 117, folder 2876), and Alan Levy's "Ezra Pound: a Jewish View" (Box 117, folder 2887).